Okay, it's time to get coding underway, and I think the best place to start is with our dragonfly
sprite as it's the main character, after all.
And also before we do anything, let's get rid of this cat that is on the screen as we don't need it
for all this project.
So to do this, we can either simply click this delete button next to the sprite, or maybe you've created
some cool code for it already, so you could just hide the sprite instead, and you can bring it back
any time by clicking show.
But first things first, make sure that you have this sprite selected to ensure that you're coding the
right thing.
And with that, okay, it's time to create your first script again, this sprite.
Very.
So let's think about this.
Uh, in our game to do care, we want to be able to control this dragon and make it grow some up and
down, large and right, using our keys.
So can we do that able them?
So this is where you need to think like a computer and think logically.
What are all the instructions that the computer needs in order to move with the arrow keys?
If you're up to the challenge, pause the video now and give this a go.
Try to see if you can write the script that allows the sprite to move with the arrow keys.
But if you have no clue, don't worry.
I just want you to pause and give it a moment to think about it.
Well, let's take a look at how we solve this with code.
First things first, we'll start with the when flag clicked block, as this will start our script automatically
when we click the flag.
Okay, now we know our dragonfly needs to move around the screen, so we know we're going to need one
of these blocks in the motion group.
You might be thinking we should use this move ten steps code block as we used it to get our cat to walk
across the screen.
And yes, while we could use it to get the dragonfly to go right ten steps and left by minus ten steps,
there is a problem.
We can't get the dragonfly to go up and down with this.
So instead of using this move block, there is something much better that you should be always using
instead.
And that is this.
Change x by and change y by blocks.
Now remember how we said that our stage is seen as a grid, and our sprite can be at any point on this
grid from -240 x to plus 240 y from -180 y to plus 180 y.
So if we change our x position by a positive number, we essentially are moving our sprite to the right
of the screen.
And if it's a negative number, we are moving it to the left side of the screen.
And the same goes for changing y.
If we change y by a positive number, we're moving our sprite up, and if we change it by a negative
number, we are moving our sprite down the screen.
So now that we know all this, we can grab two of each change x and change y.
Now because remember for each we need one of them as a negative.
Now if you click on each of these blocks you can see how it moves our sprite around the screen which
is exactly what we want.
Now all we need is a way to control this with our keys instead of clicking.
So if you remember in our earlier lesson, we can do this with the sensing group of code.
And here you'll see there is this block for checking if a key is pressed, which is exactly what we
need.
If we bring this out, you can see that we can swap the space for, well, pretty much any key we like.
So let's change it to right arrow pressed.
So this is all fine, but we need to connect this.
And to do this calls for perhaps one of the most important blocks ever.
And it is found under control.
And it is the if then block.
Now remember how I said how often you will make decisions if a certain condition is true, like it's
raining outside, you will wear a raincoat.
The same concept is very important in programming.
Here we want to check if a certain key is pressed.
Then something should happen like obviously moving in a certain direction.
And I also want you to notice something very important about these blocks that you have been working
with.
Which is the different shapes, kind of like Lego pieces, and they fit together in specific ways.
Now, these shapes are designed to help you easily understand which blocks can connect to each other,
just like how certain Lego pieces can fit together.
The shapes prevent you from connecting blocks that shouldn't be joined, which is helpful to avoid mistakes
and keep your code working smoothly.
In the world of text based coding, it's crucial to make sure your code is organized and free of errors,
and basically it'll be structured quite similarly to your scratch code.
By having different block shapes and scratch, the platform guides you to create well structured and
functional code, which is similar to how Lego pieces come together to form a stable structure.
For example, you'll find that some blocks have a notch on the top and a bump on the bottom.
These blocks are designed to stack on top of each other.
Other blocks have a special C shape, which means they can wrap around other blocks like this if statement
or forever loop.
This helps create loops or controls the flow of your code.
Anyhow, with all that cleared, let's connect up this code.
So if the right arrow is pressed, we want to change x by a positive number.
So we can put that in here and then add on when flag clicked block to the top completing our script.
Right.
Let's see.
So clicking play and then clicking our right button.
Oh, that's not good.
As you can see, nothing at all happened.
And we know we have our if statement.
We are checking if the key is pressed.
So what's missing?
Well, do you have any ideas as to what's going wrong?
Basically, it's only checking once and just how when we wanted our cat to follow our mouse pointer,
checking once is just not enough.
We need the code to continuously check if the right arrow is pressed.
So to fix this, all we need to do is put all this code in a forever loop.
Now it's constantly checking to see if this condition is true.
So if we hit play again, notice how if we click the right arrow now it moves.
Great.
So now all we need to do is the same for the other keys.
Now I'm going to give you a really handy tip here.
So instead of going back to our code palette and finding the if block and this key press block, what
we can do instead is just right click the block of code you want and click duplicate.
Now you can see we have two.
And we can duplicate both of these blocks by clicking right at the top and duplicating again.
So now we have four which is all we need.
The next thing to do now is change the key pressed input.
So here we will do the left arrow.
Up arrow and down arrow.
But we're not done yet.
We now need to change what happens.
So if the left arrow is clicked, we need X to be negative.
Then if the up arrow is clicked, we need to change y and this time by a positive number.
And lastly, for the down arrow, we must change y by a negative number.
And if we play now, there you have it.
We can officially control our character.
And you are well on your way to becoming a game developer.
There are just two things I want to do now.
Now the first is quite easy.
Firstly, I just want to make this dragonfly not move so fast.
And simply all I need to do is reduce these numbers.
So I'll just halve it and change it to five and minus five.
So now you'll see our character is easy to control.
Okay, so the next thing is I want to get the ladybug to randomly glide around the screen.
So take a moment to try to see if you can do that yourself.
How can we get the ladybird to randomly move around the screen?
Well, this is actually very simple.
As we did this with our cat sprite.
If you remember, all we need to do is bring in when start clicked a forever loop and then glide one
second to a random position.
And now if you click play again.
You can see our game is really getting there.
A ladybug is moving around and we're able to control our dragonfly.
Great job on getting to this point.
We have certainly come a long way.